在 2018 年 7 月 12 日的早晨
On the morning of July 12, 2018,
世界各地的 Python 社区成员
members of the Python community all around the globe
从床上爬起来 拿起咖啡 打开了自己的电脑
woke up, grabbed a cup of coffee and popped open their laptops.
随后 一个接一个地
Then one by one,
看见了一条消息 它来自他们仁慈的独裁者：
they discovered a message from their benevolent dictator.
吉多·范罗苏姆 编程语言 Python 之父
Guido van Rossum, the man who invented Python,
这是世界上最伟大的编程语言之一
one of the world's greatest programming languages,
也许没有之一
maybe the greatest programming language,
他面向 Python 社区的全体成员写下这条消息
had written to them all.
我们不难想象出 Python 的粉丝们阅读这条消息时的画面
So imagine all those Python fans reading these words.
“我没想到在我已经如此努力的情况下
I don't ever want to have to fight so hard
仍有这么多人对我的决策不满
and find that so many people despise my decisions.
我想把自己从决策过程中完全抽离出来
I would like to remove myself entirely from the decision process
给自己一个永久的假期 让自己一辈子都不做仁慈的独裁者
by giving myself a permanent vacation from being benevolent dictator for life.
你们都要靠自己了
You will all be on your own.
我不会指定继任者
I am not going to appoint a successor.
那么你们接下来要如何做呢
What are you going to do.
创立民主制度吗？或者保持无政府状态？”
Create a democracy? Anarchy?
在这条简短却惊人的消息发布之后
With that simple but earth-shattering note,
吉多·范罗苏姆
Guido van Rossum,
这个被 Python 社区追随了几十年的人…
the man that the Python community had been following for decades ...
好吧 他基本上就这样退出了
Well, he basically just bowed out.
这条消息被命名为 “权力交接”
His message was titled "Transfer of Power,"
它将永久的改变 Python 的格局
and it would change the landscape of the Python language forever.
不过除此之外 它又引出一个问题
But more than that, it called into question
所有的这些编程语言在未来要怎样衍变与壮大呢？
how all our programing languages were going to evolve and thrive in the future.
是否应该由一个仁慈的独裁者把控
Were languages supposed to be run by one Benevolent Dictator,
赋予它们形体和一致性？
giving them shape and coherence?
又或者 在开源世界里 编程语言的发展与变化是否应该更像口语
Or, in our open source world, were languages more like spoken languages,
取决于所有语言使用者的行为？
things that grow and react
according to the behavior of a whole bunch of different speakers?
Python 社区 这个成长速度远超其他语言的社区
The Python community, the fastest growing community of any language out there
很快就会找到这个问题的答案
was about to find out.
我是 Saron Yitbarek
I'm Saron Yitbarek,
这里是《代码英雄》第三季
and this is season 3 of Command Line Heroes,
一档来自红帽的原创播客
an original podcast from Red Hat.
在上一季的《代码英雄》里
Last season on Command Line Heroes,
我们探索了广袤天地
we explored a huge stretch of territory,
从游戏主题出发 到失败的艺术 再到无服务器开发
from gaming, to the art of the fail, to serverless development.
最后我们甚至追踪了一台在火星表面 来自 NASA 的火星车
We even ended up tracking one of NASA's rovers across the surface of Mars.
但是真正抓住每个人想象力的一集 似乎是
But there is one episode that seemed to really capture everyone's imagination
格蕾丝·赫柏的故事
the story of Grace Hopper.
她参与开发的编译器
Her work on compilers
导致了世上第一个高级编程语言 COBOL 的诞生
led to the first high-level programming language, COBOL.
我们随后意识到 Grace Hopper 的故事
We realized afterward that Grace Hopper's story was
不过是万千个塑造了软件开发与运维的世界的故事之一
just one of so many stories of languages shaping the world of development and ops.
新的编程语言使得我们可以连通人类与机器
New programming languages allow us to bridge humans and machines.
它们打开了一扇扇通往无限可能的大门
They open gateways toward amazing new possibilities.
因此 第三季将全部围绕这些语言展开
So, season 3 is all about those languages.
我们会谈论 JavaScript、BASIC、Go 以及 Perl
We're talking JavaScript, we're talking BASIC, Go, Perl.
当然 还有 Python
And yes, we're talking Python.
我们的旅程将从 Python 开始
Python is where our journey begins
顺着 Python 的故事
because by following the tale of Python,
我们会学到一个与所有编程语言未来相关的至关重要的事实
we learn a crucial truth about the future of all our programming languages.
在 Python 的仁慈的独裁者放弃王座之后
After Python's benevolent dictator abandoned his throne,
整个 Python 社区…呃 有些迷茫
the Python community was ... yeah, a bit lost.
你要如何在独裁者退位之后组织工作呢？
How do you organize things after a dictator steps down?
有人提议使用长老教会式的架构
Somebody suggested they can model their structure after the Presbyterian church.
长老宗是起源于苏格兰的基督教新教教派 其教会称为长老教会
长老宗采用代议民主制度进行管理 由信徒群众选出长老组成议会来统辖各个地区教会
这主意没能经得起考验
That idea didn't stick.
要弄清楚 Python 是如何重新找到领导方式的
To understand how Python did reorganize
并了解这对其它语言的未来有什么意义
and what it means for the future of languages in general,
我们必须要回到 Python 故事的源头
we have to go back to the origin of the Python tale.
我所有代码都用 C 写 这让工作变得有些枯燥
Well, I'm writing all this code in C and it's getting kind of tedious.
本尊驾到：吉多·范罗苏姆 Python 的仁慈的独裁者
That's the man himself, Guido van Rossum, Python's Benevolent Dictator.
范罗苏姆曾经为
Van Rossum had worked for years at
阿姆斯特丹著名的 CWI 工作数年
Amsterdam's famous Centrum Wiskunde & Informatica,
CWI = 荷兰国家数学与计算机科学研究中心 原文为荷兰语
在那里他协助开发了 ABC 编程语言
where he helped develop the ABC programming language.
ABC 被认为是吉多发明 Python 时非常重要的灵感来源
现在 他将描述他使用 C 工作时
Here, he's describing the moment he was working in C
发现对一个全新编程语言产生需求的时刻
and saw a need for a brand new language.
仍然感觉还是有着很多 bug 并且开发速度缓慢
It still felt like there were lots of bugs and it was just slow going.
我在想 呃 如果这里支持 ABC 语言
I was thinking, hmm, if we had an ABC implementation here,
我可以在十五分钟内写出整个登录程序
I would just write a whole login program in 15 minutes,
然后我可以接着开发账户管理之类的功能
and then I would move onto the account management program or something,
但是用 C 进行开发 却要花掉我一整个星期
and in C, it takes me a week each.
我开始设想 要提出一种
I somehow started thinking about coming up with a way
可以在 Amoeba 环境中使用 ABC 语言特性的方法
to use some of ABC's features in the Amoeba environment.
在研究编程语言的历史时我们发现
Here's something we discovered
in studying the history of programming languages.
没有什么东西是全新的
There's no such thing as brand new.
它们全都是为了拼凑出解决方案而从旧语言借鉴来的
They all borrow from old languages in order to cobble together solutions.
语言会不断的变化、发展、开枝散叶
Languages morph, they evolve, they branch.
当范罗苏姆被种种可能性弄得迷茫时
When van Rossum was getting frustrated with the possibilities out there,
他设想出一个可以弥合 C 与 Shell 编程两者间隙的编程语言
he imagined a language that could bridge the gap between C and shell programming.
一些场景下使用 C 语言往往是牛刀杀鸡
C was often overkill,
与此同时 用 Shell 脚本又常常让人感到繁琐
but at the same time, shell scripts felt too cumbersome.
二者之间的最佳结合点 正是 Python 的栖身之处
There was a sweet spot between the two, and that was a spot that Python filled.
当范罗苏姆 在 1991 年首次发布 Python 时
When van Rossum first released Python in 1991,
它的影响犹如神启 尤其是对系统管理员而言
it was a revelation, for sysadmins especially.
这是一种前无来者 功能全面的脚本语言
Here was a full-featured scripting language
unlike anything that had come before.
第一次使用 Python 时
The first time that I used Python,
我立即就爱上了它
I absolutely fell in love with it.
这是 Emily Morehouse
That's Emily Morehouse,
目前 Python 核心开发者中的五位女性之一
one of five women currently working as a core developer on Python.
我最初学习的是 C++ 它与 Python 有巨大的不同
I think seeing such a stark difference between a first language like C++
在换用 Python 之后 我觉得
and then moving into something like Python,
你能通过感受这种不同 感受到 Python 在设计上的优雅之处
you are really able to see the elegance of the language and the language design itself.
你不必去应付
You're not necessarily having to deal with
内存管理的毛糙的底层实现细节
any of the hairy implementation details of memory management,
它可以既快又好地构建一些项目
and it was such a great way to build things so much faster,
更不必说它还有着如此广泛的应用领域
and build things for a much wider variety of applications.
Python 吸引力的关键之处 就在于它的可扩展性
Key to Python's attractiveness was its extensibility.
举个例子 像 ABC 这样的语言 在设计上是固化单一的
A language like ABC, for example, is monolithic in design.
无法形成一个能够真正帮助改善它的社区
There's no way for a real community to help define how the language will work.
反观 Python
By contrast,
在设计之初 范罗苏姆就希望 Python 是开放的、易于扩展的
van Rossum wanted Python to be open and extensible from the beginning.
进行软件设计时
When approaching software design,
你往往需要用到一些现有的软件或系统
you often will have to take either existing software or other software systems,
并且要让它们能够协同工作
and get them all to work together,
其实软件设计的核心价值之一
and one of the very true values of how you can design software
就在于确保它的可扩展性
is making sure that it's extensible.
听起来不怎么费脑子
It sounds like a no-brainer,
但并非每一个语言都像 Python 这样
but not every language has achieved the level of extensibility
有着与生俱来的强可扩展性
that Python had right from the start.
事实上 一门不具备可扩展性的语言
The truth is, if a language doesn't have extensibility baked into it,
大概率会随着自身的发展而崩溃
there's a good chance it will end up collapsing under its own weight as it grows.
Python 有一个非常有趣的设计
Python has been designed in a very interesting way
它允许在其核心上进行扩展
that allows it to be extensible at its core.
实际上 你可以在运行时环境上对系统的不同片段打补丁
You can actually patch different pieces of the system at runtime,
假如你想要改变模块导入的方式
so if you want to switch out how modules are imported,
或者你想改变你的字符串类型或整数类型
or you want to switch out your string types or your integer types,
Python 允许你用相当容易的方式去实现这些事
Python allows you to do all these things fairly easily.
Python 可扩展性的核心
At the heart of Python's extensibility
是所谓的 C 扩展 或者说是 C 模块
is something called C extensions, or C modules.
因此 Python 在设计上就为你提供了对其它语言的切入点
So Python has actually been designed to give you an entry point to other languages,
本质上来讲 如果你可以写出 C 扩展或 C 模块
and essentially, if you can write a C extension or a C module
可以用它去桥接其它数百种语言
that can then bridge to hundreds of other languages,
你可以黑入 Python
you can kind of hack Python.
这完全取决于用户根据自身需求调整语言的能力
It's all about the user's ability to adapt the language to their own needs.
所以说 Python 按照吉多·范罗苏姆的设想
So Python, as Guido van Rossum envisioned it,
绝不会局限于独裁者的个人视野
was never going to be limited to one dictator's vision.
他的“权力交接”备忘是必然要到来的
His “Transfer of Power” memo was a long-time coming.
范罗苏姆明白社区影响力所能产生的力量
Van Rossum understood the power of community influence,
这是一种能够使所有人都聚集于同一顶“大帐篷”之下的力量
the power of bringing everyone under a big tent.
没错 他最终被冠以独裁者称号
Yes, he ended up getting called a dictator,
但却是一名仁慈的独裁者
but it was benevolent dictator.
我认为 Python 社区变得如此多元化
I think one of the reasons why Python has become such a diverse community
原因之一就是吉多本人
is because of Guido.
Python 现在能够拥有女性核心开发者
Python has female core developers now
正是因为吉多希望有这样的改变 并一手推动其实现
because Guido wanted that change to be made, and made it happen himself.
Python 软件基金会的主席 Naomi Ceder
Naomi Ceder, the chair of the Python Software Foundation,
曾在一次演讲中说：
once gave a keynote where she said,
“你为语言本身而选择 Python 但留住你的会是社区”
"Python. Come for the language, and stay for the community."
这可能正是吉多·范罗苏姆留下的最棒的礼物
And that may be Guido van Rossum's greatest legacy.
不仅仅是 Python 语言
Not just Python,
他更是为整个 Python 社区都创造了空间
but the Python community he made room for.
他不仅在语法意义上为 Python 提供了可扩展性
He made Python seriously extensible,
某种角度来讲 他也在社交意义上提供了扩展性
but it was, in a way, socially extensible, too.
永远都为新来者留有位置
It always had room for human additions.
Python 有着大量不同的应用领域
You have so many different applications of Python that
而社区又如此多元化
that your community is then, by definition, and by construct, very diverse.
所以它真的、真的扩展了社区的边界
So it's really, really broadened the community reach.
Emily Morehouse 是 Python 核心开发者
Emily Morehouse is a core Python developer
与 Cuttlesoft 的工程总监
and Director of Engineering at Cuttlesoft.
Python 降世之后 它就开始了前所未有的增长
Once Python hatched, it started to grow like nothing before.
我看到一个 Stack Overflow 上的图表
I'm looking at a Stack Overflow chart
统计了每门语言被提及的次数
that shows the amount of chatter they get on each language,
对应着 Python 的那条线仿佛坐上了火箭
and Python's line is rocketing.
2018 年 在 Google 搜索 Python 的人数
In 2018, more people did Google searches for Python
比搜索金·卡戴珊的还多
than for Kim Kardashian.
这门语言如此火热 以至于它加入了“最常用编程语言”头衔的竞争
All that excitement has it jostling for the title of most-used language
它的对手里包括了 Java C 和 C++
against options like Java, C, and C++.
那么 对 Python 的偏爱究竟来源何处呢？
So, what's with all that love, anyway?
为了找到答案 我找到 Michael Kennedy
To find out, I caught up with developer Michael Kennedy,
他活跃在 Python 时代精神的中心
who lives at the center of the Python zeitgeist.
他主持着两个专注于 Python 的播客：
Michael hosts not one, but two podcasts devoted to Python.
Talk Python to Me 和 Python Bytes
Talk Python to Me, and Python Bytes.
我们会在展示内容里放上对应的链接以便大家查看
We'll throw some links in the show notes so you can check them out.
Michael 将要和我一起讨论 Python 是如何真正迈出大步的
Michael and I got chatting about how Python really hit its stride.
如果你看过分析报告或总结报告一类的东西
If you look at the analytics and the surveys and stuff like that,
会发现 2012 年是一个重要拐点
it really seems to be that 2012 is a strong inflection point,
而发生在 2012 年左右最具意义的事情莫过于
and the most significant thing that happened around 2012
数据科学社区换掉了 R 之类的东西
is the data science community switched away from things like R,
开始真正专注于 Python
some other stuff, to really focus on Python.
这件事发生以后 Python 社区就有了更充足的劲头
Ever since that's happened, there's been even more momentum there,
也有了更多的机器学习库
more machine learning libraries.
像许多流行的机器学习库
A lot of the popular machine learning libraries, for example,
都会首先考虑支持 Python
are Python first,
此后才会考虑其他语言
and then they'll consider other languages.
嗯 我也这么认为
Yeah, that's been my understanding, too.
当我想到 Python 时 我知道它可以被用作 Web 开发
When I think about Python, I know it can be used for web development;
我也认识许多仍然在使用 Python 来写 Web 应用的人
I know a lot of people who still use it to build web apps.
但我感到 Python 如今真正的核心更多是在数据科学领域
But I feel like the heart of it nowadays is more in the data science part of things.
你认为是什么导致了这件事情发生？
What do you think led to that happening?
为什么数据科学社区抛弃了那些
Why did the data science community leave things,
或者我不应该叫抛弃 而是疏远了 R 之类的工具?
or I can't say leave, but move away from things like R?
对 正是如此
Right, exactly.
从何而来呢？
Where'd that come from?
我认为这种转变中是有两件事在起作用
I think there's two things at play in that transition.
其中之一就是 Python 作为一种“真正的” -
One of those things certainly has to do with Python being a real,
所谓的“真正”编程语言
in quotes, "real" programming language,
它既可以写一些简单的东西
in the sense that you can build simple things.
例如构建图形或数据分析工具等等
You can build graphs and data analysis tools and whatnot.
它也可以用来构建 Instagram 和 YouTube
But you can also build Instagram and YouTube and all these other ...
以及其他类似的复杂应用…
Yeah, yeah!
是的
相对于 R … 之类的东西而言
Whereas things like R ...
Literally.
显而易见
对 这很显而易见
Yeah, literally, quite literally.
有很多应用都是由 Python 来编写的
Those are written in Python.
所以他们之前在使用一些其它的编程语言时
So there are other languages they were using,
例如 R
like R at the time,
它是专精数据科学工作的 科学统计类的编程语言
was sort of scientific, statistics type programming language that did data sciencey stuff.
如果他们想要写一个 Web 应用来展示他们的结果
But if you wanted to go build a web app to show off your results,
那么 他们要用什么来实现呢？
well, what are you going to use?
Node 或者 Python 还是…
Node or Python or ...
这导致他们没办法一直使用 R 这样的语言
You couldn't stick with it.
对 说的很好
Yeah, that's a good point.
所以说 Python 拥有相当棒的能力 …
So Python has this really nice ability that it ...
它是一种“真正的”编程语言
Basically, it's a real programming language.
这是其一
So that's number one.
第二点是 Python 十分独特 它被我称为
Number two is, Python is pretty unique in this, what I call ...
…全频谱语言
It's a full-spectrum language.
我所谓的全频谱的意思是指
What I mean by full spectrum is,
假如我是一名生物学家、天体物理学家或别的什么
I can be a biologist or astrophysicist or something,
当我想要处理一些数据
and I want to explore a little bit of data,
想要加载一个 CSV 文件并运行一些指令得到图像时
I want to load up a CSV file and run some commands and get a picture.
我无需理解什么是类、静态方法、主函数、无返回值
I don't need to understand classes, static methods, static main void,
编译或者链接
compilation, linking.
你不需要像某些编程语言那样
You don't have to go through all the stuff that some programming languages do
为了入门而去学会这些
just to get started.
我只用写几行代码 键入指令 程序就可以运行
You can do just a couple lines of code, type a command, and it runs.
但是 你也可以用它去搭建像 Instagram 之类的软件
Yet, you can build things like Instagram and so on.
它可以成为绝对专业的系统
It can grow into this absolutely professional system that you can use,
但是你不会在一开始就被逼迫着
but you're not forced to understand
去理解大型应用的一切深层抽象
all these deep abstractions that are meant for large applications right away.
你可以根据自身需要来使用它
You can adopt them as you need it.
我说得有道理吗？
Does that make sense?
对 对 非常有道理
Yeah, yeah. That makes a lot of sense.
刚才我们谈论到 2012 年的拐点时
So we talked about that inflection point around 2012,
我搜索了一些关于 Python 的资料
and when I was looking and doing some research about Python,
Python 的确是世界上被 Google 次数最多的编程语言
Python is actually one of the world's most Googled, Google searched, coding languages.
哇
Wow.
你感觉它现在确实被大家青睐 并且仍在成长之中吗？
Do you feel like it's really picking up and growing at this point?
我认为它真的被青睐并处于成长之中
I do think it's picking up and that it's growing.
在我们谈论到的过去几年里
In those last number of years we talked about,
有相当多的企业集团都选择使用 Python
there's certainly more enterprise groups that are using Python.
而他们曾经的选择是 .NET、Java 有时是 C
It used to be .NET, Java, maybe some C.
这就是回答 并且现在 Python 开始走出属于自己的路
That was the answer, and now Python is starting to make its way in,
我认为它在某些场景下被格外倚重
and I think it's getting sideloaded into those environments somewhat,
关于这个 我指的是那些数据科学家们
and by that, I mean the data science folks.
就像 显然
It's like, well, obviously
我们用到的 Jupyter Lab 和它的 Notebook 之类优秀应用
we're going to use Jupyter Lab and all the cool notebook stuff.
全都是 Python 造就的
That's Python.
数据科学没有祖传代码的负担
Data science doesn't have such a legacy code base story.
如果我想开发一个新的项目
If I'm going to start a new project
用来分析广告活动或科学结果
where we're exploring some ad campaign or some science results,
它不会对一堆陈旧的东西 保持着庞大的依赖关系
that doesn't have a huge dependency on old stuff.
模型和数据都会过时
Models and data expire,
因此对于数据科学世界而言 切换技术栈或保持最新状态要容易得多
so it's more easy for the data science world to switch technologies or stay more current.
说得不错
That's a good point.
嗯 谢谢
Yeah, thanks.
嗯 听上去 Python 不会很快停止成长
Yeah. And it sounds like it's not going to stop growing anytime soon.
而是保持增长的趋势
It sounds like it's going to keep growing,
甚至这种增长的势头越加迅猛
and the momentum is still going to carry it forward.
你认为对这种增长与前进的势头影响最大的事情是什么呢
What do you think is going to influence that growth the most, moving forward?
我感觉这就像滚雪球
I feel like it's this ball rolling downhill.
Python 有如此多我们可以使用的库和软件包
We have all the libraries and packages you can use with Python.
现在更是多到难以置信
It's a ridiculous number that we have now.
一两年前 这个数字大概是 10 万
A year or two ago, it was 100,000.
而现在我们已经有了 17 万个包或项目
Now it's 170,000 packages or projects.
Wow.
哇
而现在我们已经有了 17 万个包或项目
Now it's 170,000 packages or projects.
你可以仅仅写几行代码
You can just, in a couple lines of code,
然后说 噢 我要做机器学习
oh, I'd like to do machine learning.
有人在会议上向我们展示了一个例子
Someone at the conference showed us an example of,
他们训练一个机器学习系统
here's how we're going to train a machine learning system
给它提供大量人脸的图像
to be given a bunch of faces of people,
并告诉系统他们拥有什么类型的眼睛
choose what type of eyes they have.
是圆眼睛？或者椭圆形眼睛之类的东西
Do they have round eyes, do they have oval eyes, things like that.
似乎这会帮助你决定妆容之类的
Apparently this drives the kind of makeup you have or something.
噢 哇
Oh, wow.
这位女士的演讲十分精彩 然后她说
This woman did a great presentation, and she said,
这是训练模型的代码 让大家提问
here's the code to train this model,
and then to ask it questions.
而代码从头到尾只有十五行
And it was 15 lines of code from beginning to end.
接着你看 就像她说的那样
And then you have, here's your thing that tells you,
Wow.
哇
接着你看 就像她说的那样
And then you have, here's your thing that tells you,
你提供一张照片 模型就会知道你的眼睛像什么
given a picture, what your eyes are like.
噢 天哪
Oh my goodness.
这种类型的项目势头十足
The momentum of those types of things,
这些简洁 但功能极为强大的东西
these little, super powerful things,
你可以直接通过一些包来导入 这真是厉害极了
you can just bring in through these packages is ridiculous.
Wow, that's so cool.
哇 这好酷
是不是很疯狂
Ain't that crazy?
Wow, that's so cool.
哇 这好酷
是不是很疯狂
Ain't that crazy?
好吧 让我们暂停一下对话
Okay. Let's pause that conversation for a sec.
我们会在稍后听到更多 Michael 的观点
We're going to hear more from Michael later on,
但我现在想要回头来强调一些事情
but I want to go back and underline something.
使 Python 这些令人惊叹的特质成为可能的源头
It's what makes all those amazing Python qualities possible in the first place.
Python 社区
The Python community.
Python 成功的一个决定性因素就是这个庞大的、反应迅速的社区
A defining part of Python's success is that huge, responsive community.
此时此刻 正如我们在范罗苏姆离开时看到的那样
At the same time, as we saw with van Rossum's departure,
社区的规模已经庞大到让人难以接受
the size of that community can be overwhelming.
想象一下你不得不背着整个语言包袱的样子
Imagine having to carry the hangups of an entire language around with you.
某种角度来说 吸引了如此庞大的社区
In a way, attracting such a massive community
让保有一个终生独裁者的主意变得站不住脚
made the idea of a single dictator for life just untenable.
范罗苏姆恐怕未曾设想
Van Rossum wasn't necessarily prepared
他的语言会收到如此巨大的反响
for how huge a response his language was going to receive,
但是 几乎完全自发地
but, almost organically,
社区成员将 Python 的邮件列表
community members pulled together Python's mailing list,
新闻组、网站
its newsgroup, its website,
以及最终通过 PEP 讨论语言变化的流程汇集在一起
and eventually, the process for discussing language changes via PEPs.
PEP 是“Python 改良提案”的缩写
That stands for Python Enhancement Proposals.
所以 尽管有着独裁者的名号
So, despite the dictator title,
范罗苏姆仍致力于搭建一个用户可以真正传达意见、
van Rossum was building a language that you could really talk back to,
参与其建设的语言
a language that users could help build.
我敢打赌 尽管他在离开的那一刻感到沮丧
I'm betting that despite his frustration at that moment of departure,
但范罗苏姆明白 一个活跃的社区
van Rossum knew that a dynamic community
给他的语言带去的好处 要远胜他离去而折损的
would give more to his language than it could ever take away.
我叫 Diane Mueller
My name is Diane Mueller.
Diane 是红帽云平台的社区开发总监
Diane's the Director of Community Development at Red Hat for the cloud platform.
在过去的 30 年里
Over the past 30 years,
她目睹了开源社区的强劲发展
she's witnessed a powerful evolution in the strength of open source communities,
尤其是 Python 社区 给她留下了极为深刻的印象
and she's been impressed by Python's community in particular.
Python 社区做得太棒了…
The Python community has done amazing ...
他们带来了大量行为准则的概念 比如说 关于会议
They brought in the concept of codes of conduct for conferences,
多样性奖金 各种各样的东西
diversity scholarships, all of that sort of stuff.
通过引入不同的声音以及不同的观点
By bringing in the different voices and the different perspectives,
我们得到了一个更好、更具创新性的项目
we get a better and more innovative project
它必定能够留存得更久
that will live on longer,
并有望为更多的人带去更好的体验
and hopefully work better for more people.
即便他们犯错了
Even the mistakes they made,
也会开诚布公的进行处理
they handled openly and transparently and through collaboration with the community
以前 我在别处见过这种精神的消磨殆尽
after seeing that sort of spirit wither away
它萎缩了 让位于硅谷创业公司中的“兄弟”文化
into a bro culture from Silicon Valley and startups,
“兄弟”文化 (Bro Culture)：这种现象被认为是一种工作场所中广泛存在的不良文化
对于女性 它表现为大男子主义 对于男性 它表现为一系列的规训 要求他们与特定的气质相吻合
Python 就像带我回到了我创业的地方
Python felt like coming back home to the roots of where I got started,
围绕着它的社区也像是回到了往日
and the community that had been around back in the day.
它真的相当鼓舞人心 非常惊艳
So it was pretty inspiring and pretty awesome.
能够鼓舞如此多的人 是因为 Python 在最初就重新定义了
Inspiring largely because Python redefined what it means
成为社区一员的含义
to be part of the community in the first place.
我讲过吉多·范罗苏姆即使是在引退之际
I mentioned that Guido van Rossum started championing women in the community,
仍倡导了在社区里对女性的拥护
even as he stepped down.
此外他也在更宽泛的意义上帮助了社区的拓展
But he also helped widen the tent in a more general way.
个人为集体带来的远远不止是代码贡献
Individuals bring a lot more to the table than just code contributions.
绝大多数社区管理者或是项目主管
Mostly community managers and project leads
都把精力集中在如何促进大家为他们的项目做出贡献
focus on trying to get people to contribute to their project,
而在 Python 社区里
and in the Python community,
大家会鼓励你参与文档工作
people were really highly encouraging you to work on documentation,
或是帮助会议的举办
to help run the conferences,
以及对多样性的促进
to help promote diversity.
这里有许多不同类型的事让你参与
There were all sorts of other things you could do
都可以使你成为 Python 社区的一份子
to be part of the Python community.
所以这个想法 即社区贡献不仅仅局限于代码
So that idea, that contribution isn't just about code,
像参与活动、相互学习和教育
it's about participation, it's about learning and education,
以及大量的文档工作
and it's a lot about documentation,
这些对许多人而言都是融入 Python 社区的方法
was the way into community for a lot of people.
当然 我们还有许多路要走
Of course, we've still got a ways to go.
用人制度仍然注重于技术
Meritocracy is still very technically focused.
没人会怀疑这个
No one's going to doubt that.
但我想你也看见社区管理和社区管理者的理念了…
But I think you also see the belief that community management and community managers ...
我们也是社区重要的一份子
We're skilled parts of a community,
不只是被雇来组织活动的
as opposed to just the person we hired to create our events for us.
对 Diane 而言 范罗苏姆正式放弃他独裁者角色的决定
For Diane, van Rossum's decision to officially abdicate his dictator role
是全局变化的一部分
is part of a global shift.
这代表着编程语言的建设开始摆脱陈旧与单一
It's moving away from older, monolithic kinds of language-building.
我想我们可能已经摆脱了这种模式
I think we might have moved on from that model,
尽管每过一段时间 我就会听人说
though every once in a while, I hear someone say,
“是的 我终生都是这个项目的仁慈独裁者 ”
yeah, I'm the benevolent dictator for life of this project,
但我并不认同
and I'm like, yeah, I don't think so.
Diane Mueller 是红帽社区发展总监
Diane Mueller is a Director of Community Development at Red Hat.
在吉多·范罗苏姆发出那份令人瞠目结舌的《权力交接》之后
By the time Guido van Rossum sent that jaw-dropping “Transfer of Power” memo,
Python 社区自身便成为了权力中心
the Python community was a powerhouse unto itself.
随着项目的成熟发展 出现新的治理模式是正常的
It's common for projects to adopt new governance models as they grow,
并且正如我们所见
and in many ways, as we've seen,
这些人已经做好准备 要来管理自己的语言了
these folks were ready to take charge of their own language.
但我仍然好奇 整件事最终是如何收场的？
But I still want to know, how exactly did that pan out?
范罗苏姆退场之后究竟发生了什么
What happened after van Rossum stepped away.
让我们回到与 Michael Kennedy 的对话中来找到答案吧
Let's go back to our conversation with Michael Kennedy to get some answers.
…他离开了 Python 社区在没有他的情况下过得怎么样呢？
... back and away from Python, how has the community been doing without him?
嗯 社区的状态其实还不错
Well, the community has been okay,
但我们的上层…有点卡住了
but we've been in ... at the highest level, kind of a stasis.
运行时和语言基本上陷入了停滞
The runtime and the language just basically had to go into a coma.
有一些有趣的提案 有些比较麻烦
There were proposals for interesting things, and they were sometimes complicated,
有些又挺简单
but sometimes really simple.
比如 嘿 要不然我们每一年发布一次 Python
Like, hey, wouldn't it be great if we could ship Python yearly instead of every 18 months,
而不是每 18 个月
这样跟年度会议绑在一起 语言变化会变得更可预测 就类似这种事
so it's a little more predictable, tied around the yearly conference, things like that.
Sure, yeah.
是啊 嗯
这些都是无法做出定夺的
That couldn't be decided,
因为在他引退之后 还没有方法去做决策
because there was no way to make decisions after he stepped down.
他基本上只留下一句 我去度假了
He basically said, I'm going to go on vacation.
全靠你们了 你们自己搞明白怎么继续运行下去
This is up to you guys, you have to figure out how to keep running this.
我不会告诉你们怎样去做决策或怎么去运营
I'm not even going to tell you how to decide how to keep running it.
这些麻烦现在是你们的了
This is your problem now.
这听起来非常有戏剧性
That sounds dramatic,
但仔细一想
but check this out.
还记得之前提到的 Python 改良提案（PEP）吗？
Remember those Python Enhancement Proposals,
那些用于接受社区反馈的 PEP？
the PEPs that allowed the community to give feedback?
它们可以拯救大伙
Well, PEPs to the rescue.
有一系列提案试图为 Python 社区确立新的治理模型
There was a series of them
trying to determine new governance models for the Python community.
最大的新闻是他们最终决定选择其中之一
Well, the big news is they've decided on one of those,
叫做“指导委员会” 有五名成员
called the Steering Council, which is five people
我确信五人的投票权是相等的
- I believe they all have equal votes -
他们最近选举出了五个人
and they've recently elected those five.
所以 这不是一个人的责任 而是所有人的责任
So instead of it being on one person's shoulders, it's on all of them.
我感到十分高兴的一件事是
One thing that I think is really nice is that
吉多·范罗苏姆也是他们的一员
we have Guido van Rossum as one of those members.
注：吉多于2019年被选举为委员会成员 但在2020年的选举中放弃了提名
他在帖子中提到 自己无意再担任委员会成员 因为感到这份职责是一件“苦差事”（chore）
他引退后说 “我不能作为…”
He stepped away and said, I cannot be the single source of ...
“所有人想要改变和反馈的压力的唯一的发泄口”
all the pressure of people wanting changes and feedback.
但是他还在 他没有完全抛弃这门语言
But he still, he didn't completely run away from the language.
他仍然是一个核心开发者 并且加入了指导委员会
He's still a core developer, and he's on the Steering Council.
因此他仍然保留了发言权 但无需再独自承受一切
So he still has some say, but he doesn't have to take it on entirely,
这真是非常棒
which is pretty cool.
我很好奇 这一切在现实世界里是怎么奏效的
I'm wondering how that works out in reality,
我感觉如果我是指导委员会的一员
because I feel like if I'm on the Steering Council
和语言的创造者坐在一起
and I'm sitting next to the creator of the language,
我可能会倾向于赞同他所说的任何意见
I'd probably tend to agree with whatever he says.
对 确实如此 在平局的情况下 最终取决于吉多
Right, exactly. All things being equal, ties go to Guido.
对 是这样
Yeah, exactly.
我不确定 但我认识指导委员会的一些人
I don't know. I do know some of the people on the Steering Council,
他们一直以来都是社区的贡献者和开发者
and they've been constant contributors and developers,
可能超过了…在代码的意义上
maybe even to ... at a code level,
十五年来给 Python 写的代码比吉多本人写的还多
more so than Guido for 15 years.
他们也都是非常深入的参与者 并且相当有主见-
So they're also pretty deeply involved and pretty opinionated, so-
…而且相当投入
And invested.
对 投入巨大
Yeah, certainly invested.
所以我认为这是行之有效的
So I feel like it's going to be okay.
另外 我觉得吉多的态度是 我仍然想参与其中
Also, I feel like Guido's probably like, I still want to be involved,
但不愿把自己的意志强加于人
but he's probably done trying to impose his will on people,
否则一切都和原先没什么两样…
because that will just put him right back into the same ...
我认为他可能倾向于呆在压力没那么大的位置上
I think he's probably going to take a more relaxed position.
好的 我想知道
Okay. I'm wondering,
你会不会觉得“仁慈的终生独裁者”这种模式
do you feel like this model of having a benevolent dictator for life,
在一门语言的初创阶段 是必须的？
is that model almost required at the beginning of a language,
是不是这样才能让项目启动运行
in order to get it up and running,
才能让它能拥有激进的设计 获得革命性的优势？
in order for it to be radical and have these breakthrough advances?
我认同 我认为 大多数由委员会进行的设计 并不惊艳
I do. I think stuff, mostly design by committee, is not super.
在早期 有太多决策需要进行
So in the early days, so many decisions about,
语言如何工作？
how does the language work?
要不要用分号？
Does it use semicolons?
怎么做这 怎么做那？
How does it do this, does it do that?
所有这些内容都很难由委员会来决定
All that stuff is really hard to committee decide,
但是 Python 至今已经有 25 年的历史了
but Python is over 25 years old now.
它有这么多人参与其中
It's got so many people involved in it.
我认为现在 它遵循的是一个非常好的模式
I think now, that this is a pretty good model.
他们还有过辩论 是否应该换上一个替补的 BDFL
They also debated whether or not there should just be a replacement BDFL,
我们选谁当国王呢？
who do we elect now to be our king?
不过 他们最后没有采取这个提议
They decided against that, though.
好 如果 BDFL 的位置有这么重要
Okay. If that BDFL position is so important,
我想知道 社区需要依赖他多久呢？
I'm wondering, how long does a community need one?
听上去吉多是自行做出决定：嘿 太过分了
It sounds like Guido decided on his own, hey, this is too much.
这样下去不行 我不干了
This is not sustainable anymore, I'm not doing this anymore.
但是 假如他没有做出这样的决策 我想知道
But if it wasn't his decision, I'm wondering,
是否有一个最佳的时机让这个人退出
is there an optimal time where that person should step down
让大家走向一个更民主的状态呢？
and we should move to something a little bit more democratic?
嗯 一定会有的 对吧？
Yeah, there has to be, right?
我认为这个时机应该存在
I think that there probably is.
一个人难以
It's hard for one person to
与社区、技术的脉搏以及新的趋势一直保持紧密联系
still be completely connected with the pulse of the community
and technology and the new trends,
说个数 大概 40 年
let's say, 40 years out.
这是件极其困难的事
That would be super difficult,
因此一定要有这个转换
so there's got to be this switchover.
我不能确切的说究竟在什么时候
I don't really know where it is,
但我认为必须得等到其他人
but I feel like it's got to be after you have other people
相比 BDFL 做出了更多的贡献
doing more work than the BDFL is doing.
随着核心贡献者和开发者越来越多 然后你就 嗯 我要去度假了
More core contributors and developers, and you're just like, well, I was on vacation,
看看这些新的事情发生了 它还能活下来
and look at all these new things that happened, and it survived.
类似这样的事情
Something to that effect.
嗯 就好像是社区在准备好后会自己告诉你
Yeah. It's almost like the community will tell you when it's ready.
对 正是如此
Right, exactly.
Python 社区的生涯仍将继续
The Python community is still taking on a life of its own,
这里就是我们暂时告一段落的地方
so that's where we'll leave them for now.
Michael Kennedy 的两个播客
Michael Kennedy is the host of two podcasts
会持续追踪 Python 之后的历程
that'll keep on tracking their progression in the meantime.
欢迎订阅 Talk Python to Me 和 Python Bytes
You can check out Talk Python to Me and Python Bytes.
你听说过被称为古代雅典立法者的梭伦的故事吗？
Have you ever heard the story of Solon, the guy known as the lawgiver of ancient Athens?
他是个很酷的家伙
Pretty cool guy.
在梭伦为雅典的民主制度建立宪法之后
After Solon established a constitution for Athenian democracy,
他选择了流放他自己
he went off into a state of voluntary exile.
因为他清楚 继续执政只会增加他成为暴君的风险
That's because he knew there was a danger he'd become a tyrant if he stayed in power.
我觉得吉多·范罗苏姆就像是当代梭伦
I guess Guido van Rossum is a latter day Solon,
为我们提供了数十年的标准实践
giving us decades of standard practice,
有点像是一部宪法
which is a bit like a constitution.
他建立起一门出色的编程语言
Here's a guy who set up a brilliant programming language,
一个能真正由开源社区自己运作的语言
a language where an open source community could really make it their own.
然后 他给予他们一个权力转移的时刻
Then, he also gave them that transfer of power moment,
他在那时告诉他们 全靠你们自己
where he told them, you're on your own.
我不再是你们的独裁者了
I'm no longer your dictator.
他确保了一定是由社区 而非他本人
He made sure that it had to be the community, not himself,
来推动 Python 前行
that carried the Python mantle forward.
某种意义上 吉多·范罗苏姆的“权力交接”
In a way, Guido van Rossum's “Transfer of Power” memo
是开源世界中所有编程语言的共同宣言
is a manifesto for all programming languages in an open source world,
因为任何语言随着其社区的发展
because as any language grows its community,
终将面临唯有社区才可以解决的挑战
it ends up taking on challenges that only the community can solve.
在《代码英雄》的第三季中
In season 3 of Command Line Heroes,
我们会对编程语言的世界进行深入的挖掘
we're doing a deep dive into the world of programming languages.
一门编程语言之所以能获得影响力
Languages gain influence
正因为它是解决新问题的利器
because they solve a new problem in some powerful new way,
在本季的剩余时间里
and for the rest of the season,
我们会探索
we're uncovering the superpowers baked into
JavaScript、Perl、COBOL、Go
JavaScript, Perl, COBOL, Go,
以及更多语言所具备的超能力
and so much more.
在下一集 我们会了解到 BASIC 的故事
Next episode, we'll learn the story of BASIC,
以及它带来的 关于“每个人的第一门编程语言”的启发
and what it teaches us about everybody's first language.
如果你想更深入地研究 Python 或你在本集里听到的其他内容
If you want to dive deeper into Python or anything else you've heard on this episode,
请转至 redhat.com/commandlineheroes
head over to redhat.com/commandlineheroes.
最后 我是 Saron Yitbarek 直到下期 请坚持编程
Until then, I'm Saron Yitbarek. Keep on coding.